Are you a good judge of character?
你是个善于判断他人性格的人吗？
Can you make an accurate judgement of someone's personality based only on your first impression of them?
你能否仅凭第一印象，就准确判断出一个人的性格？
Ironically, the answer lies as much in them as it does in you.
具有讽刺意味的是，答案既取决于对方，也取决于你自己。
One of the first people to try to identify good judges of character was US psychologist Henry F Adams in 1927.
1927年，美国心理学家亨利·F·亚当斯是最早尝试界定“识人高手”的人之一。
His research led him to conclude that people fell into two groups – good judges of themselves and good judges of others.
他的研究得出结论，人可以分为两类——一类善于自我认知，另一类善于洞察他人。
Adams's research has been widely criticised since then, but he wasn't entirely wrong about there being two distinct types.
尽管亚当斯的研究此后饱受诟病，但他提出的“存在两种截然不同类型”的观点，并非完全错误。
More on that in a moment, but first we need to define what a good judge of character is.
关于这一点，我们稍后再详谈，但首先需要明确什么是“善于判断性格的人”。
Is it someone who can read personality or someone who can read emotion?
这类人是能读懂他人性格，还是能体察他人情绪？
Those are two distinct skills.
这是两种截然不同的能力。
Emotions such as anger or joy or sadness can generate easily identifiable physical signs.
愤怒、喜悦、悲伤等情绪，往往会外显为易于识别的生理信号。
Most of us would probably be able to accurately identify these signs, even in a stranger.
即便面对陌生人，我们中的大多数人也能准确捕捉到这些信号。
As such, most of us are probably good judges of emotion.
因此从这个角度来说，或许我们多数人都是“察言观色”的高手。
In order to be a good judge of personality, however, there needs to be an interaction with the other person, and that person needs to be a 'good target'.
然而，若想准确判断他人性格，不仅需要与对方产生互动，对方还得是“易被读懂的人”。
'Good targets' are people who reveal relevant and useful cues to their personality.
所谓“易被读懂的人”，指的是那些会主动流露与性格相关的有效线索的人。
So this means 'the good judge' will only manifest when reading 'good targets'. This is according to Rogers and Biesanz in their 2019 journal entitled 'Reassessing the good judge of personality'.
罗杰斯和比桑兹在其2019年发表的题为《重新审视“识人高手”》的论文中指出，这意味着“识人高手”的能力，只有在面对“易被读懂的人”时才会显现。
"We found consistent, clear and strong evidence that the good judge does exist", Rogers and Biesanz concluded.
他们的结论是：“我们找到了确凿、清晰且充分的证据，证明‘识人高手’确实存在。”
But their key finding is that the good judge does not have magical gifts of perception – they are simply able to "detect and utilise information provided by the good target".
但他们的核心发现是，这类人并非拥有什么神奇的感知天赋，他们只是能够“发现并利用‘易被读懂的人’所提供的信息”。
So, are first impressions really accurate?
那么，第一印象真的可靠吗？
Well, if you're a good judge talking to a 'good target', then it seems the answer is 'yes'.
答案似乎是肯定的——前提是你是一名“识人高手”，且你面对的是一个“易被读懂的人”。
And now we know that good judges probably do exist, more research can be done into how they read personality, what kind of people they are – and whether their skills can be taught.
既然我们现在知道“识人高手”很可能真实存在，那么未来就可以开展更多研究，探索他们解读他人性格的方式、他们自身的特质，以及这种识人能力是否可以通过后天习得。